מזל טוב, Mazal Tov, today's דף daf is נ"ח. nun-chet. We take
up with the bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב', nun-zayin amud-bet, the two
dots. So we just had some really fascinating discussions like the גמרא
Gemara uses as an opportunity really to do some degree בבא מציעא
Bava Metzia stuff about שומר שמסר לשומר shomer shemasar lishomer and you
know if שומר שכר shomer sacha can never say that it was
נגנב nignav and get
כפל kafel because of לסטים מזוין listim mezuyan and so on. So
anyway, we now move back to more straight בבא קמא Bava Kamma
issues which are the this animal that goes into the field and
causes נזק nezek and we'll pick up with the word to quote
from the משנה Mishnah about six lines from the bottom of נ"ז
עמוד ב'. nun-zayin amud-bet. נפלה לגינה, Nafela legina, this sheep fell into
the garden ונהנית v'nehenis and it got benefit. משלמת מה שנהנית. Meshalemes
mah she'nehenis. So this is the classic idea that even if it's
not going to pay for נזק, nezek, even though it is פי
אחר peh acher and it is if you could say I don't
know רגל regel or something or שן shen הנאת הזקו, hana'at hazeiko,
nevertheless it was אונס, onus, it fell into the garden and therefore
you're not going to pay for נזק nezek but there's this idea
of paying for הנאה. hana'ah. That I got benefit from you right
and that's like it's like you know the way I described it's
like it's like your your ball, your football, got through fell into
my yard. I have to give it back to you. I didn't
steal it, it wasn't an אבידה, aveida, but it's your thing that
I got right now, right? So you know money got transferred from
your bank account into mine. I have to give it back to
you. So here you know my I got some concrete benefit from
your property you know that you lost. It's like that benefit is
being held by me and I have to restore it to you.
So that's the idea of הנאה, hana'ah, but it is only the
הנאה, hana'ah, it is not the damage. It is what I am
holding of yours as it were. So that's the idea of משלמת
מה שנהנית. meshalemes mah she'nehenis. Okay let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר
רב בנחבטה, Amar Rav benachbeta, that's when it got impacted on the
fruit, you know the fruit cushioned its fall. So the הנאה hana'ah
was was that it cushioned its fall.
And how do you assess that?
I'm not sure. That's a really good question, right? Because like like
then the הנאה hana'ah could be more than the damage, right? I
mean the fruit was worth ten bucks but it stopped my animal
from dying you know so right I don't exactly know how you
would how you would assess yeah how that. That's not like the
animal ate and the question is how much is a meal worth?
Right? So it's hard I don't know. Let's read a little bit.
אבל אכלה Aval achla but if it ate, okay, אפילו מה שנהנית
אינה משלמת. afilu mah she'nehenis eino meshalemess. So there's a bizarre idea.
It accidentally fell into your yard so I'm an אונס onus and
then it decided to eat. I don't have to pay you for
the meal. Like I don't have to pay for the נזק nezek
fine I'm an אונס. onus. Why do I not have to pay
you for the meal? So for like the הנאה. hana'ah. So the
גמרא Gemara says tries to figure this out. לימא רב לטעמיה Leima
Rav l'taameih let's say רב Rav is going according to his reasoning
דאמר רב היה לה שלא תאכל. de'amar Rav hayah lah shelo tochal.
If you remember this case I brought Reuven's block fruit into Shimon's
yard שלא ברשות. shelo birshut. Shimon's cow ate it. So if Shimon's
cow slipped on the fruit Shimon could say to Reuven you had
no right being in my רשות. reshut. You basically created a בור
bor in my רשות reshut and you have to pay me. But
if Shimon's cow ate the fruit and got a stomach ache Reuven
doesn't have there Reuven doesn't have to pay. Why not? He brought
the fruit in, he shouldn't have brought the fruit in. So because
רב Rav says היה לה שלא תאכל. hayah lah shelo tochal. The
animal shouldn't have eaten so much to have given itself a stomach
ache. In the end of the day it damaged itself. It didn't
slip on the fruit, it damaged itself by stuffing too much fruit
into itself. Okay so we somehow think that if that eating the
owner is you know you're פטור patur because you didn't bring damage
to the animal like it's a bizarre it's a bizarre parallel. Then
when my animal eats somebody else's fruit I shouldn't have to reimburse
him for the fruit. Like היה לה שלא תאכל hayah lah shelo
tochal means it shouldn't have done it. So if it shouldn't have
done it that's all the more reason why I should be paying
because it shouldn't have been eaten like it's very strange.
It should have known better than to eat too much. It should
have known better not to eat your fruit at all. That's right.
Yeah. Like in school you learned you don't take stuff that doesn't
belong to you.
Right.
Therefore you should pay for it if you do though.
Therefore you should pay for it. Okay.
Okay anyway let let's read. The גמרא's Gemara going to reject it
right away.
Yeah רש"י רש"י Rashi Rashi reads the question beats me at the
first the דיוק. diyyuk.
Oh לימא leima as a לימא בתמיה. leima bitmiyah.
אבל אכלה אפילו מה שנהנית. Aval achla afilu mah she'nehenis. Oh all
right
right.
Oh okay.
Ah that's interesting that that was the סתם stam of the גמרא.
Gemara. Oh
was that רש"י? Rashi? I think I missed that.
It's the one word רש"י. Rashi.
אמר רב. Amar Rav. Or רבנו חננאל. Rabbeinu Chananel. אבל אכלה. Aval
achla. Oh that's a very good point. Thank you I missed that.
Okay so Hillel correctly points out that the גמרא Gemara the all
רב Rav said was one word. Thank you that's an excellent point.
Let's read that again. אמר רב בנחבטה. Amar Rav benachbeta. The משנה
Mishnah said it hit. So the גמרא Gemara says what? אבל אכלה
אפילו מה שנהנית אינה משלמת? Aval achla afilu mah she'nehenis eino meshalemess?
You mean to tell me but then the לימא leima doesn't fit
so well. All right anyway. Okay. But anyway but clearly this is
a little absurd that he should eat it doesn't pay? לימא רב
לטעמיה Leima Rav l'taameih
so would this be רב Rav according to his reasoning? דאמר רב
היה לה שלא תאכל de'amar Rav hayah lah shelo tochal the animal
shouldn't have eaten so much to have caused itself a stomach ache.
אמי הכי השתא Ami hachi hashta what type of comparison is that?
אימא
דאמר רב התם היה לה שלא תאכל Eima d'amar Rav hasam hayah
lah shelo tochal היכא דאזיקא היא heicha d'itzika hi where the animal
got damaged itself by
eating too much fruit. Fruit. But when my animal eats לאזוקי היא
לאחרני, l'azokei hee l'achrinei,
when my animal causes damage to other people, דפטורה למישלמי, d'ptura l'meshlumei,
that I should be exempt from paying, מי אמר? mi amar? What
logic is that? My animal ate fruit, why should I be exempt?
And even if you say I should be exempt from נזק nezik
because it was what do you call it, because it was an
אונס, oness, why should I be exempt from returning the הנאה? hana'ah?
Right? So this doesn't make any sense. אלא ela says the גמרא,
Gemara, לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka'amar. Okay, לא מיבעיא אכלה lo
mibaya achla דמשלמת
מה שנהנית. d'meshalmet mah she-nehenit. So now it's, right, now your הילל's
Hillel particularly appropriate. If רב Rav only said the one word בנחבטה,
benichbeta, it's easier to change the context of that word. נחבטה nechbeta
doesn't mean דווקא נחבטה, davka nechbeta, נחבטה nechbeta means even נחבטה. nechbeta.
Okay, the משנה Mishna is talking about נחבטה nechbeta because it's a
bigger חידוש chiddush to talk about נחבטה. nechbeta. לא מיבעיא אכלה, lo
mibaya achla, of course, if the animal fell באונס b'oness and then
it ate, דמשלמת מה שנהנית, d'meshalmet mah she-nehenit, you would pay what
you benefited. That's the classic מה שנהנית. mah she-nehenit. It's not חייב
chayav as a מזיק, mazik, but it ate a meal, you pay
for the meal. Okay, so that goes without saying.
שן, shen, שן shen is a היזק. hezek. Why?
Yeah, because it was an אונס. oness. The case is it falls
to the field באונס. b'oness. נחבטה ומשלמת. nechbeta u-meshalmet. Right. אכלה achla
after נפילה דאונס. nefila d'oness. Okay, right. But the context is אונס.
oness. So then we have, we've already learned, if it was אכלה
ברשות הרבים achla birshut harabim or in this case it's an אכלה
ברשות הניזק achla birshut hanizak but it fell באונס, b'oness, that you
pay for a meal, that's an obvious נהנית. nehenit. אבל נחבטה, aval
nechbeta, but I might think that the משנה Mishna isn't talking about
נחבטה. nechbeta. אימא מבריח ארי מנכסי חבירו הוא. eima mavriach ari minechasei
chaveiro hu. Let's say what you're all, what the owner is doing
is he's doing a מצוה. mitzvah. He's like chasing a lion away
from somebody else's field. So somebody's animal was about to get damaged.
I think we discussed this the other day, I don't remember the
context, but about oh yeah, about the case about like not being
מהנה mehana for somebody's thing, like passively not saving somebody's property that's
being endangered. Okay, this animal was about to be injured and you
jumped in unwittingly, your property did it for you, and your fruit
saved this animal from injury. So יישר כח, yasher koach, you did
a big מצוה, mitzvah, you saved somebody's property from injury. So you
should maybe you shouldn't be rewarded for doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Didn't
your mama ever tell you that a good deed is its own
reward? Right? So therefore so I would say in that case אימא
מבריח ארי מנכסי חבירו הוא, eima mavriach ari minechasei chaveiro hu, you
chased away a lion from your friend's property,
you prevented damage, you intervened and prevented damage from occurring to your
friend's property. ומה שנהנה מהנה לא משלם, u-mah she-nehena mehana lo meshallem,
and they shouldn't have to reimburse you for having their property having
been saved. Because let's say, I don't know, let's say you saw
that again, my iPhone case. My iPhone's about to get run over
by a car. You see it, you stop, you wave the car,
you have it stop. I say, thank you so much, what a
big מצוה, mitzvah, give me the iPhone. You'll say, now pay me
for the iPhone. I was מהנה mehana you, you now have an
iPhone, otherwise you would have had a crushed iPhone. Okay, so we'll
get to that. But the גמרא Gemara starts with an idea that
I might think that if you saved somebody's property, right, then that
was doing a מצוה mitzvah and it was great that you did
it, but another way of thinking about this, which is not exactly
what the גמרא Gemara is saying, but it goes back to your
point, Michael, is how do you figure out the הנאה? hana'ah? Is
that I don't have any more value than I started with, I
just haven't lost value. You stopped me from a loss. Or if
my animal has a meal, I have more value and I have
to pay you for that meal. If I've just still have the
animal because it didn't get destroyed, that was always my property to
begin with, so there's really no הנאה hana'ah from you. The הנאה
hana'ah I got from you was preventative, not adding something to my
property. Okay, so that seems to be so there's two ways of
understanding what the הוה אמינא hava amina is because now the גמרא's
Gemara going to make distinctions. Why מבריח ארי mavriach ari should not
get reimbursed. Okay? Is it that if you're doing a מצוה, mitzvah,
you don't get reimbursed for מצוות? mitzvot? That's a basic idea, in
general there's all these questions about can a doctor get, a doctor
really isn't allowed to charge. A rabbi is strictly other allowed to
charge because you're doing a מצוה, mitzvah, you're not allowed to charge
for doing a מצוה. mitzvah. The only reason a rabbi and a
doctor can charge is because of what's called שכר בטלה, sechar batala,
opportunity cost, that you're paying me to not have gone to another
profession and to have spent my time learning medicine and to not
be doing other things. So you're not paying me for my service
as a doctor, you're paying me for what I could have been
doing otherwise. Of course, that's really not how it works out, because
then if I was, because then I would be charging you the
same for a check-up and for
surgery because it's the same amount of time that I'm spending. Anyway,
but that's the principle. You're not allowed to collect for doing a
מצוה. mitzvah. That's one way of framing this. The other way is
the point that I just said, which is that there's really no
הנאה hana'ah that I got. It's not that I've increased value, I've
not received, you've just prevented loss. So let's take a look where
the גמרא Gemara goes. Okay, but that makes much sense. רב Rav
says נחבטה. nechbeta. Not only נחבטה, nechbeta, even נחבטה. nechbeta. There's a
חידוש chiddush here about נחבטה, nechbeta, that you pay מה שנהנית. mah
she-nehenit. Okay, אבל נחבטה, aval nechbeta, I might think, אימא מבריח ארי
מנכסי חבירו הוא, eima mavriach ari minechasei chaveiro hu, you chased away
a lion from your friend's property, you prevented damage, you intervened and
prevented damage from occurring to your friend's property. a lion from your
friend's field and מה שנהנה נמי לא משלם, ma she-nehene nami lo
meshallem, you shouldn't even pay מה שנהנה, ma she-nehene, קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that you do pay. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. ואימא הכא נמי, ve-eima hacha nami, ואימא הכא נמי, ve-eima
hacha nami,
let's say that! Let's say you shouldn't get to any הנאה, hana'ah,
you shouldn't have to give back, right? It was just מבריח ארי,
mavriach ari, why do you pay מה שנהנה? ma she-nehene? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, here's the difference. מבריח ארי מנכסי חברו מדעתו
הוא. mavriach ari minichsei chaveiro mi-da'ato hu. Normally,
that's when somebody does it, a person consciously acts. Mike runs in
the street and stops the car from running over my iPhone. Okay,
האי, hai, this case, לאו מדעתו הוא. lav mi-da'ato hu. Mike is
not consciously acting, his property is doing it for him, and therefore
he is entitled to some reimbursement. What's the difference? Even you could
say when my property stops your thing from getting damaged, I'm not
doing a מצוה, mitzvah, right? The whole concept is the reason I
can't get any money out of it is because I was doing
a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so it was nice that my property, whatever,
but if I'm not acting and making a conscious choice or whatever,
I'm not doing a מצוה, mitzvah, right? So passively my property helped
you. So the whole idea of that מצוה mitzvah which prevents me
from the right to be paid or get some compensation is not
a
factor. Okay, that's I think like the easiest way to say it.
Another way to say it is is that if I am doing
it, like I am making like a conscious choice, so my sort
of conscious choice to do it comes with an implicit acknowledgment that
I am doing this like a selfless act and I am doing
it without any expectation for payment, right? If it's not a conscious
choice to do it, then there hasn't been that implicit understanding that
I'm not hoping to be reimbursed for this. All right, but I
think the probably more likely it's the question of whether you frame
it as a מצוה mitzvah act or not. All right, so one
difference is it was just his property did it on its own,
so it wasn't a מצוה mitzvah act. So then, ironically, he's entitled
to be reimbursed, okay, even though it came with less effort. אי
נמי, i nami, or another way of explaining it is, מבריח ארי
מנכסי חברו לית ליה פסידא. mavriach ari minichsei chaveiro leit lei pesida.
This is what Mike said, which is most obvious. That is when
there comes a no loss, meaning I can't get paid for my
personal service for running in and stopping the car. Okay, for yelling
at the lion. Oh, pay me, that's $100 for that little service.
No, you can't get paid for your service. But can you get
paid for your expenses? Okay, so האי, hai, אית
ליה פסידא. it lei pesida. Here there is a loss. And if
there is a loss, I'm at least entitled to get reimbursed. Now,
you're not getting reimbursed though, ironically, for your expenses, right? If you
were reimbursed for your expenses, you would get paid for דמי נזק,
demei nezek, the full damage, right? You're getting some out, but because
there was loss, and it came at a loss to me, the
person who did this wonderful מצוה, mitzvah, at least I can recoup
my expense and probably is the lesser of הנאה hana'ah and the
expenses. I imagine it's the intersection, right? I'm not entitled to get
more than my expenses. I can't get paid for personal service. That's
the idea of מבריח ארי. mavriach ari. And I can't get and
I can't get more than reimbursed like more than the הנאה hana'ah
that I gave the person. But probably the lesser of the two,
right, I am entitled to be reimbursed. To degree that that person
benefited, to the degree that that is equal to my expenses, I
can at least get reimbursed for my expenses.
Which then would most likely be the amount of הנאה hana'ah practically,
because
in this case, right, that gets back to your point, like if
the whole sheep didn't get splattered and it brought destroyed $10 of
fruit, so the הנאה hana'ah is at least $10. Right. So that's
why the phrase נהנה nehene is a funny phrase. But right, I
would agree that in most cases, if you're really saving the sheep,
then the מה שנהנה ma she-nehene becomes the דמי נזק. demei nezek.
So if you go and you so to speak save that iPhone,
right? Yeah.
And
there's a puddle there and your suit gets all filled with mud.
Right. So he's obligated to pay the cleaning bill?
I guess, I mean, we've got interesting questions like let's assume we
don't get into questions of could you have avoided the puddle or
whatever. Right. That was like a necessary נזק nezek that was going
to come. Right. Right, so he yes, exactly, exactly, because then I
got benefit from you that came at some loss to you. And
even though you were doing a מצוה mitzvah in the whole thing,
right, you don't get paid for your מצוה, mitzvah, but at least
you get reimbursed for your for your losses, right. So, yeah, and
there's there's cases like that about the case, I mean, although it's
not so פשוט, pashut, because there's a classic case where we're walking
down the street and I've got a barrel of wine and you've
got a barrel of honey, and honey is worth a lot more
than wine, and both and your barrel breaks, and I spill out
my wine to collect your honey, and I can't ask you to
reimburse me for for my wine. So, it's I mean that's why
you have this huge תוספות, Tosafot, because תוספות Tosafot tries to sort
of deal with all of the different cases.
Okay, what are you doing?
What's your question? I know, so we could sit and read this
whole תוספות Tosafot together, but we're not going to. Okay, so anyway,
but okay, but those are some of the issues, all right? So
it's a really interesting case about number one, not being able to
be paid for personal service, the question about fundamentally do you consider
there to be הנאה hana'ah here because there's no benefit that is
no additional value that is gained but it is a tremendous prevention
of loss. Is that... consider to be הנאה hana'ah in the first
place, right? And then these other factors about the costs of the
person, the הפסד hefsed of the person, and the conscious decision of
the person and the act of the person, to what degree making
it more of a מצה מצוה matza mitzvah or you know, and
more or less opportunity to be reimbursed. Yes.
If I remember correctly, there are also these cases like you know,
where you're supposed to support your wife, you go on a business
trip and then I go in.
Right. Those are exactly all the cases תוספות Tosafot discusses. Okay, so
these are a lot of סוגיות בש"ס. sugyos b'shas. And yes, and
a nice big תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, yes.
I don't know if you've addressed it, but if the person who
owns the property, from his point of view, an animal just fell
in and damaged his property. Right. He's not thinking about necessarily doing
a מצוה.
mitzvah. That's exactly why the גמרא Gemara says you should be entitled
to be reimbursed because when it happens all by itself without your
conscious involvement, it's not even framed as מבריח ארי mavriach ari and
doing a מצוה. mitzvah. It's framed as I suffered a loss because
of your animal, I should get something back. Right. So that's exactly
the first answer of מדעתו. mida'ato. Okay, that when it was not
a conscious choice or whatever, then it's not framed as מבריח ארי
mavriach ari and doing a מצוה. mitzvah. It's framed as I suffered
a loss because of your animal, I should get something back.
Because that's the
irony, the less of a מצוה mitzvah it is, the more you're
entitled to be reimbursed.
Right. If I said like I, you know, this is a place
where animals could fall or something like that, so I'll make sure
I cushioned it or something just in case and something happens, then
I wouldn't be.
Exactly, exactly. All right, so it's a really fascinating סוגיא sugya as
you could see like a lot of other סוגיות sugyos that deal
with it. So here we're just obviously touching the tip of the
iceberg. תוספות Tosafot is the iceberg, our גמרא Gemara is the tip.
Okay, so now, so now let's continue. But now we get to
the animal slipping and causing damage. So let's get back to the
גמרא. Gemara. היכי נפלה? Heichi nafla? How if it fell באונס be'ones
and that's why you're פטור patur when it, you know, at most
you pay מה שנהנית, ma she'nehenis, but you're פטור patur for נזק
nezek because it fell באונס? be'ones? How did it fall? Which is
like a funny question, like what do we care? Because we only
care because we might discuss certain scenarios that are debated whether they
constitute אונס ones or not, right? Like for example, the גמרא Gemara
said, right remember the גמרא's Gemara discussion whether נתקלה פושע nitkala poshea
or not? What about נתקלה nitkala of an animal? Let's say the
animal just tripped, it was a clumsy animal and tripped over its
own legs. Like what constitutes an אונס? ones? So we're raising it
because we know there's going to be a debate. Okay, so רב
כהנא אמר שהוחלקה במימי רגליה. Rav Kahana amar she'huchleka b'meymei ragleha. It
slipped in its own urine. That's clearly an
אונס. ones. רבא אמר שדחפתה חברתה Rava amar she'dchaftah chavertah that its
fellow animal pushed it down. מאן דאמר שדחפתה חברתה Man d'amar she'dchaftah
chavertah that its fellow animal pushed it down, that that constitutes אונס,
ones, כל שכן שהוחלקה במימי רגליה, kol she'ken she'huchleka b'meymei ragleha, certainly
if it slipped in the urine. ומאן דאמר שהוחלקה במימי רגליה, U'man
d'amar she'huchleka b'meymei ragleha, but if you only think that it slipped
in its urine, אבל דחפתה חברתה aval dchaftah chavertah if its fellow
animal pushed it down, פשע, pasha, then the owner, like because the
animal, whatever, but the owner is negligent and משלמת מה שהזיקה, meshalemet
ma she'hizika, you have to pay. Why? דאמר ליה, D'amar lei, but
I'll tell you why.
Because your animals from the same herd that the same owner?
Yes, from the same herd.
Yes, from someone else's?
No, not from somebody else's. From the same herd. Right. If it's
somebody else's then we can get into interesting cases of like צרורות,
tzrorot, you know, one animal using the other's like a צרור tzror
to damage or whatever. Anyway, no. דאמר ליה, D'amar lei, yes, but
from the same herd. That the owner of the field says to
the owner of the sheep, איבעי לך לאעבורי חדא חדא, Iba'ei lach
le'avorei chada chada, you should make them go single file. You know,
didn't you ever hear ראש השנה כבני מרון, Rosh Hashana k'vnei maron,
right? רועה עדרו מעביר צאנו, ro'eh edro ma'avir tzono, right? So anyway,
you should make them all be going single file. Okay. אמר רב
כהנא. Amar Rav Kahana. Now that becomes an interesting question, right, about
when I am taking my sheep out to graze, so they're not,
you know, we normally talk about שמירה shmira that they're locked up
in the pen. What is the constituent sufficient שמירה shmira when I'm
taking them out to graze, right? So here it's saying well if
you're passing on something that's got certainly there's an ability to fall
down, right it's not level ground, part of being responsible is that
they're going single file. Like what else would be? So I want
to stop for a minute and look at this short תוספות Tosafot
at the bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב. nun-zayin amud bet. נפלו לגינה,
Naflo l'gina, right fell into the garden, this is our case, והזיקה
משלמת מה שנהנית. v'hizika meshalemet ma she'nehenis. So everybody see that little
תוספות? Tosafot?
Yes, that תוספות Tosafot says נ"ז עמוד ב.
nun-zayin amud bet. So תוספות Tosafot says והוא
שאינה יכולה לירד,
v'hu
she'eina yechola leired, that would be only be a case where you
had to go by like a cliff and it fell down the
cliff or whatever into the guy's field if it could not have
climbed down the cliff
by itself. דאם כן אפילו נפלה משלמת מה שהזיקה, d'im ken afilu
nafla meshalemet ma she'hizika, you would pay even if it fell, even
if it fell באונס. be'ones. Why? דתחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס הוא. d'techilato
b'phshiah v'sofo be'ones hu. Because it started by פשיעה. p'shiah. What are
you doing walking your sheep... Yeah, but assuming what we're talking about.
What are you doing walking your sheep by where it can go
down, walk down a cliff and get into some other guy's field?
So then is that פשיעה? p'shiah? I can't walk my sheep near
other people's fields that it could walk into? Like where the heck
am I supposed to walk? I mean, I can only walk them
out in the wilderness. So if you take a look at this
little הגהות הגר"א Gahot HaGra with this little א, aleph, everybody see
this little א aleph in the square brackets? The הגר"א Gra in
the right-hand
margin? He says נדמ"ט, nadmet, which doesn't mean nota bene, it means
נכתב בצידו. nichtav b'tzido. Okay, which is a marginal note. It's like
on the right-hand margin here middle of the page. He says והרא"ש
חולק על זה. v'ha'Rosh cholek al zeh. What'd you
saying
נ"ב Nun-Bet means?
נכתב בצידו. Nichtav B'tzido. Yes, נכתב בצידו. Nichtav B'tzido.
Okay, as opposed to in English where NB means Nota Bene. Okay,
והריב"א v'haRiva חולק על זה cholek al zeh וכתב v'chasav
דאין זה d'ein zeh פשיעה. peshia.
Walking your sheep by somebody else's yard where the sheep could walk
into the yard is not negligent. וכי אוחזנה v'chi ochezna בזנבה biznava
וילך? v'yeilech?
What, are you supposed to hold the sheep by the tail wherever
you go? Like, you know, what do you have to do? You
have to walk around with a walking pen? You have to have
all your sheep on a leash? You know, so it's an interesting
question. Right, I mean, I'm sure it's a question that dog owners
deal with. I'm walking my dog, right? I mean, that's why dog
owners have to have them on a leash. But if you're walking
your sheep, do you have to have them on a leash? So
what's considered negligent? So the גמרא Gemara says negligent is having them
go by a cliff or, you know, and not go single file.
That's negligent. Okay, but walking by somebody's field where if the sheep
goes off, breaks off from the herd, it could in theory go
into that field and that, that is that negligent? Like, it's an
interesting question. How do we balance your responsibility to others with allowing
you to have a reasonable, you know, way of living your life
and of handling your sheep and of, you know, and of bringing
your sheep out into the fields? So I thought that was a
very interesting debate. Yes, Roy?
Didn't the rabbi put in a rabbinic prohibition at some point to
raise sheep in the land of Israel because they were always transgressing
and crossing?
Yeah, that's a good question. You are absolutely correct. I don't want
to go there but the whole question about right, why are we
how are we talking about raising sheep all together is a good
question. Alright, let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב כהנא,
Amar Rav Kahana, back to נ"ח עמוד א'. Nun-Chet Amud Aleph.
Is this a sheep anyway? This could be something else.
צאן. Tzon. What else is צאן? Tzon? הכונס צאן לדיר. Hakoneis tzon
ladir. The גמרא Gemara says we're not dealing with בקר, bakar, what,
goats? Okay, anyway, goats are worse for the land than sheep. Okay,
אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, לא שנו אלא באותה ערוגה. lo
shanu ela b'osah arugah. Now, at what degree back to the question
of פשיעה, peshia, so the sheep fell into the yard and it's
starting to eat and I say, oh, the eating, I'm still an
אונס, oneis, right? It fell in באונס. b'oneis. I'm still an אונס.
oneis. Okay, I only pay מה שנהנית. mah shenehinis. When do I
start to become a negligent? Like, it fell into your yard, Chanan.
Can I go home and watch TV and say yeah that was
all באונס? b'oneis? I hope it has a nice meal, I'll come
back in an hour. Okay, at what point do I become negligent
and I have to run take it out of your yard, okay,
and stop it from eating? So let's take a look. So, so,
אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, לא שנו אלא באותה ערוגה. lo
shanu ela b'osah arugah. The אונס oneis is only limited to eating
from that like, what do you call an ערוגה? arugah? Patch or,
you know, or a row actually, right?
And hopefully it's not like the longest row that goes on.
Right, right, how big is the ערוגה? arugah? Right, but here we're
trying because look, look, you know, here part of the challenge here
is that on the one hand you should say just assess every
case on its own terms. Did the owner have a chance to
intervene? Was he working as quickly as possible to get there? But
you know, that becomes really hard in a legal system to try
to assess every single case. So to try to come up with
some like basic, you know, standard parameters which are not precise in
every case, but they're good like rules of thumb and basic parameters
of defining when, at what point should he have intervened. So this
case says if he's eating from the same row, from the same
patch, fine, you're still an אונס. oneis. אבל מערוגה לערוגה, aval me'arugah
l'arugah, from going from moving from one to the other, משלם מה
שהזיקה. meshaleim mah shehizikah. At that stage we're going to call, we're
going to define you as a פושע. poshea. Okay, you should have
intervened by then. רב יוחנן אמר, Rav Yochanan amar, Rav Yochanan says
אפילו מערוגה לערוגה. afilu me'arugah l'arugah. No, even if it moves on
from one patch to the next. ואפילו כל היום כולו, v'afilu kol
hayom kulo, even if it was eating there the whole day, עד
שתצא ותחזור לדעת. ad sheteitzei v'tachzor l'daas. Until it leaves and it
returns with knowledge. Now, what רש"י Rashi means is that you know,
the owners are aware, you know, that it that it left. Let
me just uh no, there's no רש"י Rashi that says that. Anyway,
the owners are aware that it left and aware that it went
back, which presumably means, I assume he doesn't literally, although maybe I'm
just because I'm bothered with it and I'm reinterpreting it, but I
assume he doesn't literally mean that you have like, you know, you
could be aware that it's eating and continue to be פטור patur
and not do anything about it. I assume he means like we're
not going to give any limit of time. You're not going to
be חייב chayav until you know that it's eating and that you
have an opportunity to intervene. And we're just going to have to
assess every case by itself, but there's no objective, you know, or
concrete or, you know,
formalized amount of time. It could be the whole day. If you
were ignorant, if you were taking your sheep and you know and
going off and six hours later you found out what had happened
and it had been eating for six hours, you're also פטור. patur.
Until you know what's going on and are able to prevent it.
That's the way I read not literally that it leaves the field,
but until you're aware and are able to prevent it. One minute,
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, לא תימא עד שתצא ותחזור לדעת.
lo teima ad sheteitzei v'tachzor l'daas. Don't say that it has to,
now he's going to also also limit it in the following way:
don't say that it has to leave the field and then you
have to be negligent with it going back into the field. אלא
כיון שיצאת לדעת, ela keivan sheyatzas l'daas, once you knew that it
left the field, אף על פי שחזרה שלא לדעת, af al pi
shechazrah shelo l'daas, then you're liable even if it went in without
you knowing. And רש"י Rashi says even if like you were שומר
shomer it and you did a good שמירה shmira on it, you're
going to be liable once you knew that it left, that was
in the field and it left. Why? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דאמר
ליה D'amar lei the owner of the field could say to you,
כיון דילפה, keivan d'yalfa, since it was
known to or habituated to go and to eat in this field,
you know, and it liked my carrot, כל אימת דמשתמטא להתם רהטא,
kol eimat d'mishtamta l'hatam rahta, at every time it's going to break
away, it's going to run to my field, it loves eating in
my field. So now you have a heightened responsibility once you're aware,
right? We saw that before about the גמרא Gemara about an אבידה
aveida and an animal that travels, like what heightened responsibility you have
once you know that the animal has a habit and is likely
to break away. Okay, so it's an interesting debate about how much
we try to formalize an amount of time and make it objective,
which is not going to be precise and fair in every case,
but it's going to make it a lot easier as a rule
of thumb, or how much do we assess every case on its
own terms. And the second opinion says we assess it on its
own terms. It could be six hours and you could still be
פטור patur until the point when you know that it's doing it
and you're able to intervene. And then on that is added, and
the next time around you're going to be חייב chayav even if
you did a good שמירה shmira because this animal requires a special
level of שמירה. shmira. Yeah, I mean obviously there'd be a certain
point where you'd be an אונס, ones, but obviously you need a
higher level here. You need to have it on a leash from
this point forward.
Another question, let's say another animal of somebody else went and pushed
this animal?
Yeah, so I said, who knows? That might be a case of
like צרורות tzrorot of קרן keren or something like we'd have to
figure that out, you know, one is using the other animal as
a type of a כח koach or whatever. Yeah.
But why is רש"י Rashi says תחזור לדעת שלא נעשתה כראוי? tachzor
lada'at shelo na'asatah k'raui? In other words, that sounds like a פשיעה
p'shiah from the לכתחילה. l'chatchilah.
Right, רש"י Rashi is saying לדעת lada'at is not really a question
about do you know about it, you could know about it and
be an אונס, ones, you could not know about it and be
a פשיעה. p'shiah. So רש"י Rashi is reinterpreting the words לדעת lada'at
here means negligence or not negligence.
It's negligence. So why should it be a question? Of course you'd
have to pay. It's not an issue of הנאה, hana'ah, it's an
issue of...
right, that's what I'm saying. You're not חייב chayav until you're negligent.
עד שתצא לדעת ותחזור לדעת. Ad shetetzei lada'at vetachzor lada'at. רש"י Rashi
says I can know about it and still be an אונס, ones,
I could have heard about it six miles away and it's going
to take me two hours to get there. So רש"י Rashi is
just reinterpreting לדעת lada'at here in this context means you're negligent. So
the גמרא Gemara is saying you're not going to be חייב chayav
until you know about it and are able to do something about
it and are being negligent about it. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. ירדה כדרכה והזיקה משלמת מה שהזיקה. Yarda k'darkah
vehizikah meshalemet mah shehizikah. If it goes down normally without an אונס,
ones, you know, and it does damage, then that's a classic שן
ברשות הניזק shen b'reshut hanizak and you pay. Okay, so בעי רבי
ירמיה, Ba'ei Rebbe Yirmiyah, Rebbe Yirmiyah asked, ירדה כדרכה והזיקה בדמי לידה
מהו? Yarda k'darkah vehizikah bidmei leidah mahu? Let's say it goes down
and into somebody else's field and rather than eating the fruit, it
gives birth, a young, in somebody else's field, okay, and comes out
all of the, you know,
the liquid from the uterus there and so on, and that all
ruins this guy's fruit. I guess that would be a רגל, regel,
okay. So do you have to pay? So אליבא דמאן? aliba d'man?
According to
whom? דאמר... d'amar... according to the one that says תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו
באונס חייב, tchilato b'pshiah v'sofo b'ones chayav, that something that starts with
negligence, because you were negligent because you let it go into this
guy's field, and it ended off with אונס ones because the way
it damaged was a bizarre way. So the one that says you're
חייב, chayav, לא תיבעי לך, lo tiba'ei lach, I don't have a
question. That clearly you're חייב chayav here, who cares that it was
an אונס? ones? It started with a פשיעה. p'shiah. כי תיבעי לך,
Ki tiba'ei lach, what's my question? אליבא דמאן דאמר תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו
באונס פטור. aliba d'man d'amar tchilato b'pshiah v'sofo b'ones patur. If you
say that you're normally פטור. patur. מאי? Mai? What do we say?
מי אמרינן כיון דתחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס פטור? Mi amrinan keivan d'tchilato
b'pshiah v'sofo b'ones patur? Do we say that since it started with
negligence even though it ended with אונס ones you're going to be
פטור, patur, which is what we would normally say? או דילמא, O
dilma, or do we say, הכא כולא פשיעה היא? hacha kula p'shiah
hi? This is all one פשיעה, p'shiah, meaning the אונס, ones, it's
not like an unexpected, it's not like there was a פשיעה p'shiah
here and then something completely unrelated to the פשיעה p'shiah occurred over
there. No, it's all part of the negligence of letting it go
into the guy's field. Why is this included in that negligence? דכיון
דחזיא דקרבא למיילד, d'keivan d'chazya d'karva l'meylad, because you know that it's
about to give birth. So in that case, איבעי לך לנטורה. ibaei
lach l'naturei. So you're negligent also about it giving birth in somebody's
field. The negligence of letting it go in the field is of
all the things that are likely to happen in that field. And
with this animal, included in likely to happen is eating and giving
birth. So that's part of the same negligence, which makes a lot
of sense to me. Anyway, I'm not sure exactly what the ספק
safek is or how you would assess that. Okay, anyway, so you
should have known it would do that, איבעי לך לנטורה, ibaei lach
l'naturei, and you should have watched it against and protected it, you
know, from going into the field for this issue as well. So
הגמרא haGemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Okay, now כיצד משלמת
מה שהזיקה. keitzad meshalemet mah shehizikah. Now we move on from מה
שנהנית mah shenehenit and this אונס ones and פשיעה p'shiah to this
other thing that we've seen way back in the beginning of the
מסכת, masechet, כיצד משלמת מה שהזיקה, keitzad meshalemet mah shehizikah, that you
don't pay just for the damaged fruit, you don't say it ate
a bushel of wheat, how much is a bushel of
wheat, you say how much was the field worth beforehand and how
much is it worth now? And then the owner of the field
gets a lot less than the cost of a bushel of wheat,
right, because, you know, it's you don't give it as much weight
when it's in the picture of something that's a lot larger. Okay,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So מנהני מילי, minani mili,
where do you get this idea? But you don't pay directly for
the value of the eaten fruit but you pay for the depreciation
of the field. Okay, if it's growing in the field. אמר רב
מתנה, Amar Rav Masna, דאמר קרא, da’amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says:
ובער בשדה אחר, ubiyeir bisdei acheir, and it consumes in another field.
מלמד ששמין על גב שדה אחר, melamed sheshamin al gav sadeh acheir,
you look at it in the context of a field— of another
field. I don't know why another, but maybe because we're going to
standardize it and we're going to see in a minute we're going
to standardize it. So there's like two חידושים. chidushim. One חידוש chidush
is that you look at it in the context of the depreciation
of the field and of some type of a standardized model of
a field. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: One minute. האי ובער
בשדה אחר, hai ubiyeir bisdei acheir, when it says it consumes in
another field, מיבעי ליה, mibayei lei, we need it for the most
basic הלכה, halacha, לאפוקי רשות הרבים, la'apukei reshus harabim, that it's exempt
when it consumes in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, it's only when it's
in רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So the גמרא Gemara says: No. אם
כן ליכתוב רחמנא, im kein lichtov rachmana, if that's true, let the
תורה Torah say ובער בשדה חברו, ubiyeir bisdei chaveiro,
it eats in its friend's field. אינמי שדה, einami sadeh,
it eats in a field. אחר מאי, acheir mai, what—
I read that wrong. אינמי שדה אחר, einami sadeh acheir,
a different field. מאי ובער בשדה אחר, mai ubiyeir bisdei acheir, what
is "in a different field"? ששמין על גב שדה אחר, sheshamin al
gav sadeh acheir, that you assess it on the basis of another
field. Now, it's a little funny. It's like one of those classic
גמרות Gemaras where it says like: Okay, it could have said this,
it says this, we're going to say that that's extra and then
we're going to say a דרשה. drasha. But it is possible that
what the גמרא Gemara is actually saying here is a way of—
actually a question about how to read the פסוק. pasuk. And remember
many decades now, it used to be many years, now it's many
decades ago, when I was in גוש, Gush, you know, we were
learning בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, and רב ליכטנשטיין Rav Lichtenstein gave a
שיעור shiur on this and he said he wants to talk about
one letter and the letter is the letter ב. beis. And he
said and he actually tied it in because I think it was
the— it was right then, it was like פרשת שמות, Parshat Shemos,
so he tied so he said like he tied into the פסוק
pasuk where it says by— oh no, it was not by שמות,
Shemos, it was מקץ. Mikeitz. It says ותרענה באחו, vatirena ba'achu, right?
The cows grazed in the swamp, right? So he said there was
a מחלוקת machlokes רש''י Rashi and רמב''ן Ramban whether the word "in
the swamp" meant where they were grazing, they were in the swamp
when they were eating, or whether it was what they were eating.
They were eating— the אחו achu refers to like, you know, they
were consuming— they were, you know, consuming the field. So he wanted
to say the question of ובער בשדה אחר, ubiyeir bisdei acheir, is
that where it's taking place? It's consuming in somebody else's field? Or
is it— I say no, it is destroying another person's field. ובער
בשדה אחר, ubiyeir bisdei acheir, it's like if, you know, it's sort
of like saying ובער את שדה אחר. ubiyeir es sadeh acheir.
Right. Right, you'd have to argue that the ב beis is like
certain verbs are always followed by certain prepositions that gives it its
meaning. Right. That's the argument.
So it's actually— of course the funny thing is that the גמרא
Gemara says it could have said without the ב. beis. Actually, without
the ב beis it would have been clearer meant that. If it
would have said ובער שדה אחר, ubiyeir sadeh acheir, it would have
been clear that שדה אחר sadeh acheir is the object of the
consumption. But if we read the פסוק pasuk to mean that it's
saying that the thing that it destroyed was the field, it damaged
the field, so then you want to assess the value based on
the damage to the field, not to the damage to the fruit.
Right? If you see it like it damaged the house, it damaged
the field, so how much does the house or the field now
become worth less? Right? So that's the question. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this: ואימא כולה להכי הוא דאתא, v'eima kulla lehachi hu d'ata, maybe
it's all coming to tell you that הלכה, halacha, not to tell
you the הלכה halacha of
רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay. לאפוקי רשות הרבים מנלן, la'apukei reshus harabim
minalan, and how do you know to exclude רשות הרבים? reshus harabim?
No. אם כן ליכתביה רחמנא גבי תשלומין, im kein lichtivya rachmana gabei
tashlumin, but then if it was only about not— about whether you're
חייב chayiv or not, right? ובער בשדה אחר ubiyeir bisdei acheir is
the פסוק pasuk about whether you're חייב, chayiv, what act is מחייב
mechayev you. If all it was coming to tell you is how
do you pay, then this would have been written in the פסוק
pasuk about paying. Since it's written ובער בשדה אחר ubiyeir bisdei acheir
in the פסוק pasuk about the act of damage, it's also telling
you the scope of when you're חייב chayiv for damage. That you're
not חייב chayiv in a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay. מיטב שדהו
ומיטב כרמו ישלם בשדה אחר. meitav sadeh-hu u'meitav karmo yeshalem bisdei acheir.
Okay. It could have just said pay field, you know, assess based
on another field. למה לי דכתביה רחמנא גבי ובער, lama li d'chtivya
rachmana gabei ubiyeir, why did it use the word בשדה אחר bisdei
acheir in the context of causing the damage? שמע מינה תרתי, shma
mina tarti, you hear two things. Number one, only if it does
the damage in the friend's field. And number two, you pay on
the assessment of another field. And now we're going to try to
exactly put a number to that. By the way, I should say
this idea that you do not just say how much was the
fruit worth is also implied even more explicitly in the פסוק pasuk
where it says מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. meitav sadeh-hu u’meitav karmo
yeshalem. It doesn't say מיטב פירותיו ישלם, meitav peirosov yeshalem, right? The
פסוק pasuk clearly sees it as you pay a field, what is
damaged is a field. So that really does seem very clear from
the פסוק pasuk and which is why it's interesting that the גמרא's
Gemara emphasis here seems to be not so much that you assess
it how much is the field worth less, that you assess it
as a field was damaged rather than fruit was damaged. That it
almost seems taken for granted. The חידוש chidush here more is that
you look at it in a standardized context of a field, which
is what we're about to get to. Meaning, if I have— my
field, as we'll see, my field is like ten thousand acres, okay,
and it ate some fruit. How much did that depreciate the value
of 10,000 acres? Zero. My field is one acre and it ate
the fruit. How much did it depreciate? A lot. So is that
what you say? Do you look at the particular person's field? So
the חידוש Chiddush here is, I don't look at your field, how
much it was depreciated. Number one, I look at the damage to
a field, not to the fruit. But number two is, I look
at a standardized model of how I'm going to assess what size
field was damaged. And that's the חידוש Chiddush of שדה אחר. Sedeh
Acher. Is that clear? There's two points. Number one, which is pretty
clear in the פסוק, Pasuk, you look at it not that the
fruit was damaged but the field was damaged. Right? מיטב שדהו ומיטב
כרמו ישלם. Meitav sadeihu umeitav karmo yeshaleim. But number two, שדה אחר
Sedeh Acher says, I don't look at every case, every subjective case.
I assess the size of the field based on some standardized model.
You got a table or something?
Exactly, and we're going to look at that standardized model right now.
Yes.
But if you were assessing the field, what about the effort and
the work that the farmer put into producing that?
Yeah but presumably that goes to the cost, right? How much was
the field worth before, how much is it worth after? So presumably
the proportional effort that came into plowing, whatever, all that becomes translated
into the ultimate cost of the thing. If I went out and
I painted my house and I put up shingles or whatever I
did and somebody came and ripped them off, right, you don't say
wait, how much did it cost though to paint and put up
the shingles? You say how much was the house worth more because
of those shingles and how much was it worth less now that
those shingles have been ripped off? And that's how you assess the
damage, right? So that's the thing. How much was the field worth
more because of the extra fruit in it and how much has
it now been depreciated because the fruit has been destroyed? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. היכי שמינן? Heichi shamman? So how
do we assess it? אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabi Yose
birabi Chanina, סאה בשישים סאין. Seah beshishim sein. You look at for
a סאה Seah that was consumed, you look at a field of
sixty סאה. Seah. Okay, so it's sort of like ביטול, Bittul, you
go by sixty. Okay, so and that's how you look at it.
So now,
and you know, how much would a field of the size of
sixty סאה Seah be depreciated if one סאה Seah of it had
the fruit in it consumed? Right so you imagine sixty סאה Seah
of wheat and one סאה Seah has been mowed down. How much
does that affect the value of the field? So even if my
field was only two סאה, Seah, so if I have a two
סאה Seah field and one סאה Seah was mowed down, that's like
a huge impact. Okay, and your field was a thousand סאה Seah
and it's a trivial impact, for both of us we say how
much would a sixty סאה Seah field be worth less with that
one סאה Seah mowed down? And that's the whole idea of looking
at some standardized model, okay?
I don't see the difference between asking it that way and saying
how much is that סאה Seah of wheat worth to you.
Really? You don't see it? You have a thousand סאה Seah field
which is worth a million dollars and it's filled with grain. Before
it was filled with grain it was worth nine hundred thousand, now
it's filled with grain it's worth a million dollars. And a thousand
סאה Seah and somebody says oh you know actually I gotta tell
you like we had a little damage over there and one סאה
Seah was damaged. Okay, well wait, now it's only worth nine hundred
ninety-nine thousand whatever. No, fine, whatever, it doesn't affect the actual value
of it, right? But if you say how much is a סאה
Seah worth of grain, that's actually a high number. Okay, or whatever,
it's a number. All right, and if I have a two סאה
Seah field, and even if I have a two סאה Seah field,
how much is a סאה Seah of grain straight, if I ask
that question, I say twenty dollars. How much is a two סאה
Seah field worth a thousand dollars worth less because half of it
has been mowed down? Maybe only ten dollars less. I mean that's
the way people go, right?
Oh, the replacement value is going to be less.
You solved it with those words. Right, okay, that's why insurance is
worth more. Exactly.
No, it's not replacement value, it's not
like
that this amount of money can make me replace the loss.
No, what's the cost?
It's what is the depreciation. Right, it's the depreciation.
Right, and the depreciation looked in terms of a whole thing is
going to be less than the actual cost of just assessing the
item itself. Exactly. All right. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, so סאה בשישים סאין. Seah beshishim sein. רבי ינאי אומר,
Rabi Yannai omer, טירקב בשישים טירקבים. Tirkav beshishim tirkavim. Now a טירקב
Tirkav is half a סאה. Seah. So it sounds like he's saying
the same thing. Every טירקב Tirkav you assess it in sixty טירקבים,
Tirkavim, right, which is a thirty סאה Seah field. But it's not
the same because רש״י Rashi says the way רש״י Rashi explains it
is like there's a different market. Like most people want a certain
standard size field. Let's say a sixty סאה Seah field is a
standard size field. So that value, which is the most highest sort
of normal demand of the size, the per-acre cost is the highest.
Okay, I mean not the highest, that's wrong, excuse me, that's the,
actually maybe like the whatever, I don't know, the average per-acre cost.
If somebody wants to buy a specialized small field, the per-acre cost
is going to go up. Does that make sense? Right? So if
you want to buy a smaller field that most people don't have,
most people don't want to sell small little fields... Right? So if
most people don't want to sell small little fields, right? So that's
going to be a higher per acre cost. So if we assess
it based on a smaller size field, so if you had a
סאה se'ah of damage, do we say how much would that have
impacted a sixty סאה se'ah field? Would have been one number. How
much would half a סאה se'ah in a thirty סאה se'ah field
and another half a סאה se'ah in another thirty סאה se'ah field
be? That would be a higher number. Okay, because the high there
will be a higher per acre cost. So that's his position. Okay,
and we're going to have similar variations of this. I'm not going
to spell out all the things, but you get the idea. חזקיה
אמר קלח בשישים קלחים. Chizkiyah amar kelach b'shishim kelachim. Now this is
the one that seems to push back against the idea of looking
at it in terms of damage of the property. He says, no,
you look at one like קלח kelach which is a what do
you call it, like a bundle of, not bundle, a bunch of
vegetables, and you assess it amongst sixty other vegetables. You basically ask,
right, how much was it so you don't say like how much
does one bunch of carrots worth, but how much would sixty bunches
of carrots be worth as opposed to fifty-nine bunches of carrots. But
he is really a radical departure because he's not looking at it
in terms of the field. He's looking at it in terms of
the actual fruit itself. Okay, קלח בשישים קלחים. kelach b'shishim kelachim. If
I'm explaining קלח kelach correctly. I don't know, how does your English
translate קלח? kelach?
קלח kelach is a stalk.
That's what I thought. So he's really assessing it not based on
the field. He's assessing it based... he goes straight to the value
of the fruit. But he says you don't pay for one stalk,
you pay for the difference between sixty stalks and fifty-nine stalks. But
he is still not assessing it based on the field, which is
the bigger, which is the more dominant position here. מיתיבי Meitivai says
גמרא, Gemara, I'll ask you on this. אכלה קב או קביים, Achla
kav o kabayim, ודא קב או קביים, v'da kav o kabayim, אין
אומרים תשלם דמיהן. ein omrim teshalem dmeihen. You don't just say pay
the value of that and you assess it just on the fruit
itself. אלא רואין אותה כאילו היא ערוגה קטנה ומשערים אותה. Ela ro'in
otah k'ilu hi arugah ktanah umesharim otah. And you look at it
as though it was part of a small little garden and how
much would this have, you know, would this loss be. So it
doesn't sound like it's sixty times, it sounds like it's an ערוגה
קטנה. arugah ktanah. So the גמרא Gemara says, so מאי לאו בפני
עצמה? mai lav bifnei atzmah? Doesn't it mean you assess it on
its own terms? לא בשישים. Lo b'shishim. No, it means you look
at it as if it was an ערוגה arugah among sixty ערוגות,
arugot, which is not at all פשט pshat of that ברייתא. Beraita.
Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין שמין קב מפני שמשביחה. Ein shamin
kav mipnei shemashbichah. You don't assess in terms of a קב kav
because that too much increases the value.
ולא בית כור מפני שפוגמה V'lo beit kor mipnei shepogmah because that's
too injurious. מאי קאמר? Mai ka'amar? So the גמרא Gemara says, what
does that mean? What's it say? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב פפה הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Pappa hachi ka'amar. This is what
it means. אין שמין קב בשישים קבים. Ein shamin kav b'shishim kabim.
If it damages a קב kav worth, you don't assess it among
sixty... a field of sixty קבים. kabim. Okay, מפני שמשביח מזיק. mipnei
shemashbiach mazik. Because that's too beneficial to the מזיק. mazik. Because a
field of sixty קבים kabim רש"י Rashi says is a, I think
he says it's a very large field and therefore the per acre
value is very low in that in a field of that size.
So therefore the מזיק mazik gets off too easy if you have
to assess it in a field that loss. ולא כור בשישים כורים
V'lo kor b'shishim korim and you don't assess a כור kor in
sixty כורים korim מפני שפוגם מזיק. mipnei shepogem mazik. That's a small
size field where the per acre value is very high and that's
too unfair to the מזיק. mazik. Okay, so you go back to
this what we said before, the סאה se'ah with sixty סאים. se'aim.
You look at a sixty סאה se'ah field. That's a nice average
amount. Okay, מתקיף לה רב הונא בר מנוח. Matkif lah Rav Huna
bar Manoach. רב הונא Rav Huna challenges it. היי ולא בית כור?
Hai v'lo beit kor? When it says you don't... אין שמין קב,
ein shamin kav, it should have said ולא בית כור? v'lo beit
kor? Why did it say ולא בית כור? v'lo beit kor? It
should have said ולא כור מיבעי ליה. v'lo kor miba'ei lei. If
אין שמין קב ein shamin kav means you don't assess the damage
of a קב kav over sixty קב, kav, then it should have
said you don't assess the damage of a כור kor with sixty
כור. kor. Why does it say בית כור? beit kor? בית כור
Beit kor refers to like the field. Field, exactly field. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ולא כור מיבעי ליה. v'lo kor miba'ei lei.
אלא אמר רב הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרב אחא בריה דרב איקא
הכי קתני. Ela amar Rav Huna bar Manoach mishmei d'Rav Acha brei
d'Rav Ika hachi katani. Here's what it reads. Okay, אין שמין קב
בפני עצמו, ein shamin kav bifnei atzmo, בפני עצמו, bifnei atzmo, מפני
שמשביח ניזק. mipnei shemashbiach nizak. You don't assess the קב kav itself
if a קב kav was damaged. You don't just say, okay, a
קב kav of grain, how much is that worth? That's what we've
sort of been talking about all along. You don't just say that
because that's going to become a very high price and the ניזק
nizak will be get too much benefit out of that, right? Will
be reimbursed more than he deserves. ולא קב בבית כור V'lo kav
b'beit kor but you don't say let's assess how much if a
קב kav was damaged in a בית כור, beit kor, how much
would that depreciate the value? מפני שפוגם ניזק mipnei shepogem nizak because
the ניזק nizak loses out too much because that is a very
trivial amount when you assess it in such a large field. אלא
בשישים. Ela b'shishim. So rather, so as a way of parsing that
whole ברייתא Beraita to say, you don't assess the value of the
fruit by itself, you don't assess it in too large of a
field, that'll be too trivial. The way you do it is in
a field sixty times the size, okay? And that's how you assess
the value, how much would this injury have come to depreciated the
value of a field which would have been sixty times the size
of the amount of the area that was consumed. Again, though the
גמרא Gemara says you might have to figure out the right per
acre cost because a sixty סאה se'ah field has a different per
acre cost than a sixty. Yes.
Why is the person who was damaged receiving too much if it
would be based on the value of the fruit that was damaged?
It wouldn't, but the question is, is that a right... here I
am, I'm a farmer, right? I've got this, you know, field of
all this grain or whatever, right? Like is it when some animal
comes and consumes my grain, right? I mean, is it obvious that
you say the damage done was the damage to the value of
the grain as opposed to say the damage to the field? I
don't know if to me that's obvious. How do you determine which
way to define it?
How can't you say this is how much I would have gotten
if I took it to market today?
But you weren't, you mean as if you were to have harvested,
but you weren't harvesting it today and you weren't taking it to
market and you weren't winnowing it and all those types of stuff.
What it was right now was it was part of a field
and the field was the thing that was damaged.
When I use the word fruit I've conceptualized it
as like fruit to be picked. Right. It's alright. More often we're
talking about grain. But even there it would have to have been
picked, it would have to have been transported to market, right? It's
not like, you know, I... you know, so I guess the question
could be, how much would somebody have paid me today for the
right to go into my field and take this acre of stuff?
Maybe. I wonder if that's really so different than this amount. But
that's not a normal market price. People don't pay you to go
into their field, I mean unless you have an apple picking orchard.
People don't pay you to go into their field. If you want
to translate this into money, right now maybe there's a better way
of thinking about it. How would I translate what I have into
money? I could sell the whole field. That's how you get money
out of this. You don't just sell the standing grain in this
form, right? So that's I think like part of the argument, right?
If people maybe normally would sell the right to go and collect
the grain at this stage, like maybe we would think about it
differently.
Right, but that's what's really, I never thought about this, in other
words, anything can happen between now and a month from now, market
day. It could be a blight, it could be anything can happen.
Right now at this
minute, it's מחובר mechubar to the field. Right. It's what is it?
Right, exactly, exactly. And the גמרא Gemara is forcing me to ask
that question.
Right. What actually is it? Exactly, exactly. And if there really were
a market for grain at this stage of development that was מחובר
mechubar to the field and there was a clear per acre market
of that, maybe we would think about it differently.
But we don't. We have like future markets.
Yeah, I know. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Let's try to get to the end of the דף, daf, okay?
I mean,
so, okay. ההוא גברא דקץ כסיבא מחבריה. Hahu gavra d'katz kisba m'chavrei.
So a certain person cut down a palm tree of his friend.
אזל לקמיה דריש גלותא. Azal l'kamei d'Reish Galuta. He came to the
Reish Galuta. אמר ליה. Amar lei. So the Reish Galuta said to
these people who came in front of him for judgment, לדידי חזי
לי, L'didi chazi li, I actually saw that patch there with that
palm
tree. דתלתא בקינא D'tlasa b'kina and there were three palm trees growing
out of the same sort of like, you know, patch or literally
from the same stalk, הוו קיימי, Havu kaimei, and הוו שוון מאה
זוזי V'havu shavan me'ah zuzei and that whole section, that whole collection
of the three palm trees was worth
100 זוז. zuz. זיל הב ליה תלתין ותלתא ותילתא, Zil hav lei
tlatin v'tlata v'tilta, so pay him thirty-three and a third זוז, zuz,
okay? Because I know that patch of palm trees was worth 100,
you cut down one third, so pay him thirty-three and a third.
That seems pretty fair. אמר, Amar, so the guy said, גבי ריש
גלותא דדן דינא דפרסאי למה לי? Gabei Reish Galuta d'dan dina d'Parsai
lama li? From the Reish Galuta who just applies the Persian law,
why do I need him? Because the Reish Galuta wasn't a תלמיד
חכם. talmid chacham. He was the like the secular head of the
Jewish community, okay? And obviously with close ties to the Persian government.
So he said like this isn't הלכה. halacha. He's just applying Persian
law. Now, why would הלכה halacha be different? אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן.
Ata l'kamei d'Rav Nachman. He came to Rav Nachman. אמר ליה בשישים.
Amar lei b'shishim. Rav Nachman said yeah, don't pay for the damage,
just look at the value of those palm trees and then it
was 100 and now it's a third of that. Look at a
large field of palm trees and what would the loss of one
palm tree mean. So
אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so Rava said, אם אמרו בנזקי
ממון יאמרו בנזקי גופו? Im amru b'nizkei mamon yomru b'nizkei gufo? Rava
said, what are you talking about? That was a הלכה halacha about
שן. shen. That was a special הלכה halacha about when an animal
damages. If somebody goes ahead and damages personally, does an act of
מזיק... mazik... so it's not like that this raises a good question
what we were just discussing before. Is it objectively, there's no way
to define the object that was damaged to you other than as
a field? Or do we say no, that's the special הלכה halacha
by שן shen to look at it through that lens? By other
things we look at it differently, okay? And we look at it
as like as much as we can concretize on the one object
that was damaged and not in the bigger context.
אמר ליה אביי לרבא, Amar lei Abaye l'Rava, בנזקי גופו מאי דעתך?
B'nizkei gufo mai daitach? What do you think you would do when
a person personally damaged? דתניא. D'tanya. Why do you think that would
be different? Because we taught
המבכיר כרמו של חבירו, Hamavkir karmo shel chaveiro, if you basically like
המבכיר hamavkir is a funny word like בכור bechor but it basically
means you destroy, you consume like the vineyard of your friend. סמדר,
Smadar, and the grapes were like unripe. רואין אותה כמה הייתה יפה
קודם לכן וכמה היא יפה לאחר מכאן. Ro'in otah kamah hayta yafa
kodem lachen v'kamah hi yafa l'achar mikan. Because it says you assess
how much was the vineyard worth before and how much was it
worth after. What's the damage to the vineyard? Fine. ואילו בשישים לא
קתני. V'ilu b'shishim lo katani. And it doesn't say evaluate it as
one-sixtieth. Does it say you assess בששים? b'shishim? So here's a great
question. You as a person, not your animal, damages your friend's, you
know, vineyard, fruit, etc. that's growing in the field. Do you apply
this rule of בששים b'shishim or do you look at it specifically
that field? What was the market value change? That makes the most
sense, right? Let's look at the specific market value for each case
separately and not this standard ששים shishim model. So he says that's
what you think. It seems like you think that the ריש גלותא
Reish Galusa did the right thing. That when it comes to a
person who's מזיק, mazik, you look at the damage to the field,
but you don't look at it as a ששים shishim standardized model,
you look at that specific field. Okay, and that's your
ראיה. raya. סרו תו, Saru tu, גבי בהמה נמי מי לא תניא
כי האי גוונא. Gabi behema nami mi lo tanya ki hai gavna.
We have a ברייתא braisa by a בהמה behema that doesn't explicitly
say ששים shishim and nevertheless we interpret it to mean ששים. shishim.
So here too it should be ששים. shishim. Where do we say
it by a
בהמה? behema? דתניא, Detanya, we learn in a ברייתא. braisa. קטמה נטיעה.
Ketama netia. Let's say it basically cut down a, you know, a
planting, a sapling.
רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, this is a case of an
animal, גוזרי גזירות שבירושלים אומרים, Gozeiri gezeiros sheb'Yerushalayim omrim, those that make
the edicts in Jerusalem, whatever that בית דין beis din was, say,
נטיעה בת שתא, Netia bas shata, if it was a young sapling
tree of a year old, שתי כסף, shtei kesef, it's worth two
כסף. kesef. בת שתי שנים, Bas shtei shanim, two years old, ארבע
כסף. arba kesef. Fine. אכלה חזיז, Achla chaziz, now let's say it
ate a חזיז chaziz which is also, which רש״י Rashi says like
fodder, whatever some like, you know,
unripe stalks of grain or something. Okay, רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rabbi
Yossi HaGlili omer, נידון במשוייר שבה. nidon b'mishuyar sheba.
Here you go. This seems to be more what people would have
naturally said. If you look what does רש״י Rashi say משוייר שבה
mishuyar sheba means, רש״י Rashi says, רואין את המותר לפי מה שתעלה
כל ערוגה וערוגה בימי הקציר ומשלם. ro'in es hamosar lefi mah sheta'aleh
kol arugah va'arugah b'yemei hakatzir umeshaleim. So you look at how much
would this all have been worth when I would have brought it
to market and how much am I going to get less? So
you actually, which does seem unfair, why should I pay for the
future value which is not yet realized? But I see, but that's
how you assess it, yes. You look at it as the future
fruit and how much would I have lost? וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim omrim,
but the חכמים chachamim say no. רואין אותה כמה הייתה יפה וכמה
היא יפה. Ro'in osah kama hayesa yafa v'kama hi yafa. You look
at the field, how much was the field worth, how much is
it worth now, and that's how much you pay. אכלה סמדר, Achla
smadar, now let's say it was unripe. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua
omer, רואין אותן כאילו הן ענבים עומדות ליבצר. ro'in osan k'ilu hen
anavim omados l'hibatzeir.
Again, a similar idea. You look at it as if it's ripe
and how much would grapes ready for market be worth? Which seems
very unfair. וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim omrim, no. רואין אותה כמה הייתה יפה
וכמה היא יפה. Ro'in osah kama hayesa yafa v'kama hi yafa. No,
you look how much was the vineyard worth beforehand, how much is
it worth now? רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון בן
נדרא אמרו, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Nedra
amru, בזמן שאכלה לולבי גפנים וחורי תאנים, bizman she'achla lulavei gefanim v'chorei
te'einim, when is that true? When it ate just like the, very
like, the, you know, the stuff had not even begun to blossom.
אבל אכלה פגים או בוסר, Aval achla pagim o boseir, but if
the stuff had already begun to blossom, but it was unripe,
then רואין אותן כאילו הן ענבים עומדות ליבצר. ro'in osan k'ilu hen
anavim omados l'hibatzeir. Then he agrees with the previous opinion. No, once
they're starting to ripen, even if they haven't fully ripened, you look
at them as complete grape, as complete grapes. So we've introduced here
some new ideas which are not only do you assess the fruit
by itself, it's even more strict. You assess it as if it
were fully ripe fruit. So there's so on the one hand, a
pushback to the idea of על גבי שדה אחר al gabi sadeh
acher is you assess the value of the fruit and even if
it's unripe, you look at it as if it's ready for market.
Let's bracket that for a moment. וחכמים V'chachamim say you assess the
damage to the field. How do they say you assess it? How
much was it worth before, how much was it worth after? What's
missing from that? ששים. Shishim.
Where's this idea of looking at it in terms of a larger
field? Okay, so let's just finish this thought. He says, ולא קתני
בששים. v'lo katani b'shishim.
So it doesn't say there by the animal and that's a case
of an animal, it doesn't say ששים. shishim. אלא מאי אית לך
למימר, Ella mai is lach l'meimar, what do you have to say?
בששים. B'shishim. When it says the damage to the field, it doesn't
say ששים, shishim, but that's implied. We always standardize it. So הכא
נמי בששים. hacha nami b'shishim. Here too by an אדם המזיק adam
hamazik בששים. b'shishim. So this is a really fascinating idea. Do we
assess when the field, fruit in a field is damaged? We have
three possibilities, right? You look at the damage to the fruit, actually
four, the damage to the fruit as it is, the damage to
the fruit as it would be worth when it would go to
market, those two variations of the fruit, and or you look at
it in terms of the field: the damage to the field as
it is, or the damage to the field based on a standardized
model of ששים. shishim. Okay, and what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is, and the other question is, do you take what we're saying
by a שן shein and applying it to אדם המזיק? adam hamazik?
What's the basis to say that? By אדם המזיק adam hamazik maybe
we should just say look straight at the fruit. Don't do this
whole weird ששים shishim model. Okay, so that's a debate of רב
נחמן ורבא, Rav Nachman v'Rava, and we will continue with this tomorrow.
Question? Yeah. רבי יוסי... Rabbi Yose...